John Spencer Bassett Papers, 1895 - 1990
Smith College Archives
John Spencer Bassett Papers
1867 - 1928
1895 - 1990
Bassett, John Spencer, 1867 - 1928
42 UUID:ab7d164a-b336-4ce6-b91e-dc3c9d576d26
4 boxes (1.5 linear feet)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Professor of History. Contains professional papers, correspondence, news clippings and photographs belonging to John Spencer Bassett.
John Spencer Bassett was born in 1867 in Tarboro, NC, to Mary Jane Wilson and Richard Baxter Bassett, a builder and abolitionist. After graduating high school, pneumonia forced him to take a two year break before entering the Davis Military Academy in 1885. In 1888, Bassett graduated from Trinity College (now Duke University) and took a deanship there before leaving to become a history fellow at Johns Hopkins University. He received his PhD in American History at Johns Hopkins in 1894 after completing his dissertation titled The Constitutional Beginnings of North Carolina, 1663-1729. In 1892, Bassett married Jessie Lewellin, an elementary school principal. Together, they had four children, two who survived to adulthood: Richard Horace and Margaret Byrd.
Bassett returned to Trinity College for the next twelve years. Building upon the work of his predecessor, Bassett actively supported the Trinity College Historical Society for the study of southern history. Believing that everyone could collect, if not write, he worked towards acquiring a body of materials for historical research. Students, administrators, and alumni donated Confederate money, American Indian relics, travel souvenirs, and political memorabilia as well as volumes of books, pamphlets, religious and secular newspapers, maps, and manuscripts.
In 1902, Bassett founded and edited the South Atlantic Quarterly, a publication devoted to "the literary, historical, and social development of the South". In 1903, Bassett became the center of a controversy when he wrote "Stirring Up the Fires of Race Antipathy", an article in which he declared Booker T. Washington "to be the greatest man to be born in the South after Robert E. Lee". In response to a barrage of calls for his immediate dismissal, Bassett handed in his resignation from his professorship at Trinity. Surprisingly, the college refused to accept his resignation and the controversy became known as The Bassett Affair of 1903. It is regularly recounted as an exmplar of academic freedom. In 1906, Bassett left Trinity to begin teaching at Smith College as a Professor of American History. While he was teaching at Smith, Basset held several extracurricular positions in various organizations including: Old Letters Club, Library Fund, Smith College Studies in History and the Sydenham Parsons Foundation History Department.
Bassett became Secretary of the American Historical Association in 1919; he controversially supported the decision that school textbooks should be impartial and not emphasize the heroism of famous individuals. Bassett carried this idea into his own work as a writer and teacher, and he became known in the field for his objective approach to historical figures, his dedication to research and his emphasis on preserving primary documents. In 1920 he served as the chairman of the Democratic National Committee advisory group, an event which led to the reelection of Woodrow Wilson. The committee focused most of its efforts on increasing public support for the League of Nations and Women's Suffrage. Bassett sought to influence public opinion by soliciting and publishing articles written by prominent individuals in support of these charges.
Even his death in 1928 was surrounded by controversy. After being hit and killed by a streetcar in Washington D.C., the police failed to contact his family until several days after the incident, prompting an inquiry in the Washington police department.
The collection contains the professional and personal files of John Spencer Bassett. The collection contains his publications, of which the collection has twelve articles and four books, professional photographs, and a manuscript of an unpublished works called The Historians. Much of the collection is composed of correspondence with members of the academic community, with Smith College and with his family.
This collection is organized into four series:
General (1908 - 1978)
Trinity College Controversy (1897 - 1904)
Family Life (1911 - 1916)
Professional Life (1911 - 1916)
APPENDIX: Subject Index
This guide to topics within this collection was prepared by Madison White, Class of 2016.
Admissions box 3, folder 1
box 4, folder 3
box 4, folder 4
American Antiquarian Society box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 1
box 3, folder 1
American Historical Association box 2, folder 2
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 8
box 4, folder 1
box 3, folder 1
box 4, folder 3
box 4, folder 4
Columbia University Summer School box 1, folder 2
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 1
Critics box 2, folder 1
box 2, folder 2
box 2, folder 3
box 3, folder 6
box 3, folder 1
box 4, folder 4
Civil War Celebrations box 4, folder 3
Concerts, Theatre, Opera box 4, folder 3
box 4, folder 8
box 4, folder 8
box 4, folder 4
Current Events Club box 3, folder 1
Departmental Appointments box 1, folder 2
box 3, folder 1
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 3
box 4, folder 4
Fashion box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 3
box 4, folder 8
box 3, folder 6
Finances box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 3
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 8
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 3
box 3, folder 1
box 4, folder 3
box 4, folder 4
Harvard University box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 8
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 4
Lectures box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 1
box 3, folder 1
box 4, folder 3
box 4, folder 4
Margaret Byrd box 3, folder 6
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 3
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 1
box 3, folder 1
"The Mirror" box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 8
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 3
Philip's Academy, Andover, MA box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 8
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 1
box 3, folder 1
box 4, folder 3
President Burton box 3, folder 6
box 3, folder 1
box 4, folder 3
box 4, folder 4
President Seelye box 3, folder 6
Publications box 2, folder 1
box 2, folder 2
box 2, folder 3
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 1
box 3, folder 1
box 4, folder 3
box 4, folder 4
Richard's Art box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 3
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 8
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 1
box 4, folder 3
Robert Frost box 4, folder 8
Smith College Courses box 1, folder 2
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 1
box 3, folder 1
box 4, folder 3
box 4, folder 4
Smith College Studies in History box 4, folder 4
Social Events box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 8
box 3, folder 6
box 3, folder 6
Sports and Athletics box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 8
box 3, folder 6
box 3, folder 6
box 3, folder 1
Travel box 1, folder 2
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 3
box 3, folder 6
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 8
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 1
box 3, folder 1
box 4, folder 4
Trinity College box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 1
box 4, folder 3
box 4, folder 4
Trinity College Controversy box 2, folder 1
box 2, folder 2
box 2, folder 3
box 2, folder 4
W.E.B. Du Bois box 2, folder1
Woodstock, NY box 4, folder 8
box 3, folder 6
box 4, folder 3
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
The John Spencer Bassett Papers, 1867 - 1928 were created by John Bassett and donated to the College Archives.
correspondence; lecture notes; manuscripts for publication; photographs; Bassett, Jessie Lewellin; Bassett, John Spencer, -- 1867-1928; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; American Historical Association; Editors; Educational change--Southern states; League of Nations; Scholarly publishing; Smith College--Faculty; South Atlantic quarterly; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)--Faculty; United States--Politics and government--1865-1933
The following materials are available at Smith College:
Department of History Records, ca. 1900-[ongoing]
Old Letters Club Records, 1926-1937
The following are related collections not found at Smith College:
John Spencer Bassett collection, 1802-1998: Duke University Library
John Spencer Bassett papers, 1770-1978: Library of Congress
Bassett Affair Collection, 1903-2003: Duke University Archives
- Series I: General
  - Professor of History, Smith College, 1908 - 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - correspondence, 1912 - 1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - obituaries, 1928 - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - correspondence, 1911 - 1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - photographs, 1906 - 1928 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - publications, 1895 - 1925 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Trinity College Controversy, 1903
  - correspondence, 1897 - 1903 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - correspondence (November, 1903) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - correspondence (December, 1903 - February, 1904), 1903 - 1904 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - correspondence, news clippings, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series III: Family Life
  - correspondence, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - correspondence, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - correspondence, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - correspondence, misc., 1913 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - photographs 1911-1913 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - correspondence, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - correspondence, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - correspondence, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - correspondence, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - correspondence, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Series IV: Professional Life
  - correspondence, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - correspondence, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - correspondence, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - correspondence, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - The Historians, 1607-1783 (unpublished), 1911 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Historians, 1783-1850 (unpublished), 1911 (Box 4, Folder 6)